<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Matthew Huebert</title>
 <link href="http://matt.is/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://matt.is/"/>
 <updated>2011-04-02T16:54:24-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://matt.is/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Matthew Huebert</name>
   <email>matthew@huebert.ca</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Afternoon in Xela</title>
   <link href="http://matt.is/remembering/an-afternoon-in-xela"/>
   <updated>2011-03-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://matt.is/remembering/an-afternoon-in-xela</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/post-images/xela.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Xela, Guatemala&quot; alt=&quot;Xela, Guatemala&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;width:450px;margin-top:-10px;&quot; class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Xela (Quetzaltenango), Guatemala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alejandro was lanky and had a crooked thumb. I turned a corner and there he was, standing on the cobblestones in the alley. Xela was a small city but I was struck by the coincidence. I only knew a handful of locals. I wondered if I had been drawn there by the Voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mind raced like that all the time. I&amp;#8217;d be walking and a corner would arrive and at the last split second possible I&amp;#8217;d decide which way. And then I&amp;#8217;d wonder, if the Voice had told me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bible study groups there were always stories of the Voice. The Voice wasn&amp;#8217;t you, it lived inside of you and through you. Sometimes when you spoke it was really it speaking, and sometimes your thoughts were its too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;#8217;t any hocus pocus to it, that&amp;#8217;s just how it was. You were a child and when your Father wanted to speak through you, there you were, waiting for it. And ready to talk about it at the next Bible study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well this day was different because I was closer to an edge I suppose. Half mad I felt, wondering always about Voices. So with a little snap that was really easier than it should have been I stopped asking about the Voice and said enough with it it&amp;#8217;s just me. Sometimes things snap like that I guess. There&amp;#8217;s some build-up that you can&amp;#8217;t see and then one day it&amp;#8217;s different, all different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;#8217;t the full end of God yet for me but it was a start, it stopped a lot of circles from spinning in my head right there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Alejandro was just a friend I knew through a friend and we chatted for a few minutes and I kept walking and that&amp;#8217;s all. No voice that day and never after.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Trying to Matter</title>
   <link href="http://matt.is/trying-to-matter"/>
   <updated>2011-03-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://matt.is/trying-to-matter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is where I learned to swim:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/post-images/nyankunde-pool.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Pool in Nyankunde&quot; alt=&quot;Pool in Nyankunde&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;width:445px;margin-top:-10px;&quot; class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Photo: Aaron Wolcott&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pool is filled with algae because it was abandoned; it was abandoned because of war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was four when my family moved to Nyankunde, Zaire (now DR Congo). My parents had a teaching assignment there and we stayed for ten months. I was nineteen when I got the first email: &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Wearing crowns of leaves and screaming war cries&amp;#8230; tribal fighters overran a mission hospital in Nyankunde, killing patients as they lay in their beds.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; I had spent the rest of my childhood in a small, quiet town in rural Saskatchewan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels strange to be connected to such unspeakable horrors. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;During the massacre, militiamen would open up the belly of their victims and eat something directly from within the body.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; It’s not something one forgets. Nyankunde is 50km from the United Nations base in Bunia, which hits the news every so often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nyankunde we had a black cat, Rascal Snoopy Jack Huebert. (My brother and sister and I each got to pick one name; mine was Jack.) When he got scared, he&amp;#8217;d race into the fireplace and up to a hidden ledge inside the chimney. Sometimes we chased him there on purpose. He could stay up there for hours. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Through an open window, he saw dozens of women and children running toward the Congo mission compound from fields where they had been working since daybreak. Behind them were about 7,000 soldiers. Kakani closed windows and barricaded the intensive-care ward. Patients who could move were hidden under beds and in rafters&amp;#8230; Hospital staff laid many on the floor to keep them safely away from stray bullets that peppered walls and windows.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember my first baseball game. I hit the ball and didn&amp;#8217;t know what to do. People were shouting directions but I couldn&amp;#8217;t understand and then suddenly I was already out, they&amp;#8217;d thrown the ball to first base. I had to walk off the field. I was crying and felt stupid. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Despite their efforts, the Ngiti went through the 250-bed hospital, killing in their beds all patients who resembled Hemas. The dead included &amp;#8216;elderly, disabled, adults, and even a baby strapped to his mother&amp;#8217;s back.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One time, our night watchman killed a snake outside the house in the middle of the night. He pounded it into the ground with a big stick. I was asleep. The rest of my family talked about the snake at breakfast. They had woken up and got to see it. I was disappointed I&amp;#8217;d missed something so exciting. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;After the massacre at the hospital, soldiers then went from house to house looking for anyone of Hema descent; often slitting their throats and throwing their bodies outside on the ground.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- One time my dad and brother got to stay overnight with the Pygmy's in the jungle. They slept in little dome houses built into the ground out of bent sticks and covered in leaves. They ate monkey and turtle that night. We still have two sets of bows and arrows made out of those monkey tails. I wanted to stay overnight too, but I was too young.  --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At night it was pitch black, you couldn&amp;#8217;t see your hand in front of your face. The insects were loud. I don&amp;#8217;t remember being scared though. My parents were always there and I felt safe with them. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Any remaining Hema man, woman or child, found hiding in houses or in the hospital were rounded up. They were stripped of their clothes, had their elbows tied behind their back and marched to a large house in the middle of the compound and then shut in.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a man would come by to sell warm goat&amp;#8217;s milk from a rusty pot attached to his bicycle. But we ate porridge for breakfast, with powdered milk. I didn’t like milk anymore after living in Africa. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Soldiers would enter and mock the crowd who were pleading for water. They were given empty cups to drink their own urine. The soldiers told the imprisoned that &amp;#8216;this was their death chamber and they were to suffer a slow and agonizing death, but surely all would die.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My best friend was Rachael. We played together all the time. We were the same age and my mom taught us kindergarten together. One day my brother teased me about her. I got mad at him. I thought he was the one who invented making fun of boys for being friends with girls. Before that we didn&amp;#8217;t care, we just played together. We pretended that broomsticks were horses and galloped across the yard with them between our legs. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Survivors said the attackers were from the Ngiti and Lendu tribes, along with other allies. They killed people from the Bira, Hema and 16 other tribes living in Nyankunde.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a big coconut tree on the yard and sometimes you could watch local men climb it. We had a servant who would cut the grass by hand, swinging a machete. The grass made you itchy if you rolled in it. I really wanted my own machete. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;The attackers used rifles, machetes, knives, spears and arrows, said Kakani, head nurse in the intensive care ward&amp;#8230; The modern, well-equipped hospital was left a burned-out shell, stripped of everything.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember climbing up the big hill that overlooks Nyankunde, watching tall elephant grass for snakes. On the way down, I tripped and fell right into a cowpie, green and mushy. It made me cry. My mom and dad helped wipe it off, and we kept walking. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Their houses were emptied of belongings which were carried on the heads of Ngiti militiamen, across the hills to their distant villages&amp;#8230; the line of people carrying away their belongings was like &amp;#8216;a stream of ants going across the valley and over the hill.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember stepping on snails to hear the crushing sound of the shell and the squishing of the insides. I remember when I tried to climb a tree and a branch snapped, and white milky stuff oozed out, and I felt bad. I remember one time, I found a penny on a dirt road. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Among the dead was the mother of little Baraka Safari. She was killed two days after giving birth to the boy, who was found crying beside his mother&amp;#8217;s body, survivors said. He was given a Kiswahili name that means ‘fortunate journey’ by those who carried him the 93 miles to Oicha.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Nyankunde we visited Europe for three weeks on our way back to Canada. I remember sleeping in a chalet in the Swiss Alps and hearing cowbells and watching a hang-glider in the sky. There were yellow flowers in the meadow. The ceiling in the chalet was slanted. I had a featherbed blanket, it felt like four feet thick. It was cozy. &lt;em style=&quot;color:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Hospital workers and patients fled into the jungle, eventually making their way through a rainforest to a sister hospital in Oicha over 100 miles away. They lived off rainwater and sugarcane during a trek that took nearly two weeks.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-three years since living in Africa, nine years since the massacre. It hasn&amp;#8217;t been obvious what to learn from it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nyankunde attack was a microscopic blip in a complicated, massive war (5.4+ million killed). I am a tiny sliver of a whole that I cannot comprehend, one seven-billionth of humanity, connected to Nyankunde by a tenuous thread of history. It&amp;#8217;s disorienting to think about and usually I don&amp;#8217;t. Usually I just stare at myself in the mirror and don&amp;#8217;t know what to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even when thoughts remain silent or confused, I’m still left with a persistent inner tug, to try and do something that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;#8217;t verbal, and it doesn&amp;#8217;t come with instructions; I&amp;#8217;m not even sure what mattering looks like exactly. But it&amp;#8217;s a hard feeling to ignore. When I’m reading the news, or fixing a software bug, or designing a logo, or writing an email, the questions return&amp;#8230; does this matter? &lt;em&gt;Could&lt;/em&gt; it matter? What &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rarely have answers. I try to make sense of my actions, to visualize their consequence in the world, but paths of cause and effect are complex, my vision is limited, and no matter how much you learn, much of the world is inherently unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the most I can ever really say I’m doing, is trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that’s enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr style=&quot;background-color:#ccc;border:none;margin:30px 30px 10px 0&quot;/&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:11px;font-style:italic;margin-bottom:20px;&quot;&gt;Sources:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldmag.com/articles/6505&quot;&gt;On the road to genocide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bereanpublishers.com/Persecution_of_Christians/massacre_at_nyankunde.htm&quot;&gt;Massacre at Nyankunde&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/475.htm?wpmp_switcher=mobile&quot;&gt;Jungle Trek Leads Missionaries To Safety After Congo Massacre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>An App to Change the World (and pry yourself off Facebook)</title>
   <link href="http://matt.is/proposing/an-app-to-change-the-world"/>
   <updated>2011-02-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://matt.is/proposing/an-app-to-change-the-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#8217;m sitting at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startupdrinks.ca/&quot;&gt;Startup Drinks&lt;/a&gt; in Vancouver last night when &lt;a href=&quot;http://goldensword.ca/&quot;&gt;Delano Mandelbaum&lt;/a&gt;, the singular human force behind website monitoring tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blamestella.com&quot;&gt;BlameStella&lt;/a&gt;, lends me a productivity tip which I think might just change the world, if only it can be paired with a great user interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick is simple: whenever you find yourself consciously wasting your time (&lt;i&gt;time&lt;/i&gt;, you recall? that precious gift of life that &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Pincus&quot; title=&quot;Mark Pincus&quot;&gt;brilliant modern moguls&lt;/a&gt; make it their explicit goal to absorb, sponge-like&amp;#8230;), &lt;strong&gt;switch your computer screen to grayscale&lt;/strong&gt;. On a mac, you can either adjust these settings &lt;a href=&quot;http://osxdaily.com/2010/05/04/make-your-mac-run-in-grayscale-mode/&quot;&gt;manually&lt;/a&gt; or use &lt;a href=&quot;/post-images/GrayscaleToggle.zip&quot;&gt;this applescript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life in grayscale is weird&amp;#8230; disorienting, strange, foreign. You can&amp;#8217;t help but realize something in your life isn&amp;#8217;t.. quite.. right. It doesn&amp;#8217;t take long for the subtle discomfort to nudge me back into the real-world or back to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/post-images/grayscale-facebook.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us can&amp;#8217;t avoid social media, hell&amp;#8212;we rely on it. The evil is not connectedness itself, it&amp;#8217;s the trance-like suckage that turns two minute Facebook message replies into forty minute photo browsing escapades. With tens of thousands of engineers devoting their lives to various &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com&quot;&gt;forms&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com&quot;&gt;computerized crack&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;#8220;focus&amp;#8221; problem is only going to get worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need a reminder: life online is life in monochrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we have a problem: this approach is awkward without a good tool. I&amp;#8217;d like a simple app that lets me list the websites I hate but can&amp;#8217;t live without (perhaps the app could be called &amp;#8220;Nemesis&amp;#8221;?), and then forces my screen into grayscale whenever I visit them. Bonus points if it can turn my screen into an evil-looking blood-red monochrome for the worst offenders&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About This Site</title>
   <link href="http://matt.is/explaining/about-this-site"/>
   <updated>2011-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://matt.is/explaining/about-this-site</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  I built this site with
  &lt;a href='https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll'&gt;Jekyll,&lt;/a&gt;
  and it’s hosted on
  &lt;a href='http://pages.github.com'&gt;GitHub Pages.&lt;/a&gt;
  I’m using modified
  &lt;a href='http://haml-lang.com/'&gt;HAML,&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href='sass-lang.com/'&gt;SASS&lt;/a&gt;
  and
  &lt;a href='http://jashkenas.github.com/coffee-script/'&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;/a&gt;
  extensions, which make coding a lot more fun, and the
  &lt;a href='http://http://isotope.metafizzy.co/'&gt;Isotope&lt;/a&gt;
  jQuery plugin drives the
  &lt;a href='/'&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt;
  interface.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If you’re into this sort of thing, you can
  &lt;a href='https://github.com/mhuebert/matt.is-cv'&gt;view the source.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Non-Profit Tobacco</title>
   <link href="http://matt.is/proposing/non-profit-tobacco"/>
   <updated>2006-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://matt.is/proposing/non-profit-tobacco</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;#8220;Each dollar spent on cigarettes adds fuel to the sophisticated marketing of tobacco to youth.&amp;#8221;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it matter that smokers, against their own wishes, fund the marketing of tobacco to non-smokers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shrug off tobacco profits as a necessary evil, and pass off most health impacts as self-inflicted. But how can we justify investing in sophisticated marketing techniques that cause more people to smoke?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if smokers could buy cigarettes without funding tobacco marketing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smokers have a kind of leverage that non-smokers do not: the power to choose where (not) to spend their money. An independent, non-profit tobacco organization could sell cigarettes of equal quality to popular brands, benefit from cheap access to media and the good will of society, and devote all profits to fund cancer research and anti-smoking campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Originally written August 31, 2006. Edited for brevity February 28, 2011.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>